National Council On Household Employment Records 5226
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
National Council On Household Employment Records
1895-1951
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
National Council On Household Employment
Watson, Amey E.
5226
6 cubic feet
6 linear ft.
Bibliographies, photographic prints, scripts (documents).
Include materials of the National Committee on Employer- Employee Relationships in the Home, and the National Council on Household Employment (1928-1941); correspondence (carbons and originals) (1928-1941); and publications regarding household employment (1908-1941).
3834439
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183> kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
Kheel Staff, January 18, 2000
EAD encoding:
Randall Miles, February 21, 2017
Biographical / Historical
The National Committee on Employer-Employee Relationships at Home, (called the National Council on Household Employment from 1931 until its disbandment) functioned to coordinate educational and research activities of groups interested in this field.
The Committee was created in October, 1928 by a national conference on the subject of household employment held in Washington, D.C. at the invitation of the Bureau of Home Economics, the Women's Bureau of the U.S. Department of Labor, and the Industrial Department of the National Young Women's Christian Association (Y.W.C.A.). The consensus at this conference was that the hours, wages, living conditions, and working conditions of paid employees in the home needed clarification and possible adjustment. The Committee was determined to function as a clearinghouse for all groups working in the field, to stimulate relevant studies and experiments, to develop an educational program to benefit both employer and the employed, and to gradually work out standards for household employment. The initial impetus for the Washington conference came from Anetta Dieckman of the Industrial Department of the Y.W.C.A. and from Amey E. Watson, a teacher at Haverford College who was then engaged in a study of household employment. Watson served as director of the Committee until the summer of 1930 and was a member during most of its existence. The organization continued to function until 1942.
Scope and Contents
Administrative records of the National Council On Household Employment consist of minutes (1934-1942); financial records (1935-1939); membership files (1935-1939); legal documents, including model legal documents drafted by the Committee; and promotional literature about the group.
General correspondence (carbons and originals, 1928-1942) is chiefly of Lucy P. Carner (chairman of the Committee, executive, Industrial Department of the National Board, Y.W.C.A.); Mary Anderson (director, Women's Bureau, U.S. Department of Labor); Louise Stanley (chief, Bureau of Human Nutrition and Home Economics, U.S. Department of Agriculture); Amey E. Watson; Hildegard Kneeland (secretary of the Committee, Bureau of Home Economics); Anetta Dieckman (secretary, Industrial Department of Y.W.C.A.); Frank Dekker Watson (Central Committee on Household Occupations); Dorothy P. Wells (National Board, Y.W.C.A.); William P. Hill (industrial secretary, Urban League of Pittsburgh, Pa.); Mildred Taylor (Business and Industrial Department, Y.W.C.A.); Helen E. Featherstone (instructor, Frank Wiggens Trade School); Bernice Foley (industrial secretary, Y.W.C.A.); Benjamin R. Andrews (professor of Household Employment, Teachers College, Columbia University); Bertha Nienburg (assistant director, Women's Bureau, U.S. Department of Labor); Emma H. Gunther; Hazel Kyrk (associate professor, Department of Home Economics, University of Chicago); and occasional letters from the U.S. Work Projects Administration, U.S. Department of Labor (Public Employment Bureaus), National Recovery Administration, and Federal Emergency Relief Administration.
The correspondence deals with the financial situation of the National Committee; conference planning, routine administrative matters; work and problems of the Committee; the future of the National Committee; a suggested institute on labor relationships in the home to involve leading women's colleges; proposals for a voluntary agreement between employers and employees; proposals for a union or code of standardization; training of household employees; tests on general household work; reports from various states on their household employment situation and training; and personnel problems involved in household management. Additionally, the correspondence contains several letters to Eleanor Roosevelt concerning her possible chairmanship of the National Council and her subsequent refusal. Also, occasional letters from John B. Andrews (executive secretary, American Association for Labor Legislation); Frances Perkins (secretary of labor); and Anna Laylor Burdick (agent, Industrial Education, U.S. Department of Interior).
The subject files in this collection (1895-1942) document activities of a wide spectrum of organizations acting on behalf of household workers in the United States and abroad. These files include organizing literature for a domestic workers' union (1937), scripts for plays regarding household employment (1942-1943), photographs of household employees in training, notes and lectures for a course in household employment, survey data on household employment, data on various employee training courses, sample contracts, etc.
Publications (1908-1941, bulk 1935-1941) in these papers include excerpts, reprints, clippings, and writings in typescript on a wide variety of germane topics including race relations in domestic service.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Arrangement
Series I. National Council on Household Employment
Series II. General Correspondence
Series III. Conference(s) - on employee-employer relationshiops in the home, 1928 and 1931 (and others)
Sub-Series A. Correspondence Sub-Series B. Conference Documents
Series IV. Subject Files
Series V. Publications and Miscellaneous Manuscripts
Series VI. MISCELLANEOUS MANUSCRIPTS
African Americans -- Employment; Household employees; Household employees -- Labor contracts; Household employees -- United States -- Medical Examinations; Household employees -- United States -- Unionization; Household employees -- Legal status, laws, etc. -- United States; Women household employees -- United States; Hours of labor -- Domestic service -- Law and legislation -- United States; Hours of labor -- Law and legislation -- United States; New Deal, 1933-1939.; Household employees -- Labor unions -- England; Women household employees -- United States; Wages -- Household employees -- United States; Women -- Vocational education -- United States; Workers' compensation -- Household employees -- Law and legislation -- United States; Workers' compensation -- Law and legislation -- United States; Anderson, Mary, 1872-1964.; Andrews, Benjamin R. (Benjamin Richard), 1877-; Burdick, Anna Laylor; Carner, Lucy Perkins, 1886-1983.; Dieckman, Anetta M.; Foley, Bernice.; Gunther, Emma H.; Hill, William P.; Kneeland, Hildegarde, 1889-1994; Kyrk, Hazel, 1886-1957.; Nienburg, Bertha M. (Bertha Marie), 1890-; Perkins, Frances, 1882-1965.; Roosevelt, Eleanor, 1884-1962; Stanley, Louise, 1883-1954.; Taylor, Mildred; Watson, Amey E.; Watson, Frank Dekker; Domestic Workers Guild; National Committee on Employer-Employee Relations in the Home; National Committee on Prisons and Prison Labor; National Council on Household Employment; Pittsburgh Urban League; United States. Bureau of Human Nutrition and Home Economics; United States. Department of Labor; United States. Federal Emergency Relief Administration; United States. National Recovery Administration; United States. National Youth Administration; United States. Women's Bureau; United States. Work Projects Administration; Young Women's Christian Association of the U.S.A
3834439
- Series I. National Council on Household Employment
  - Constitution and By-Laws (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents
    no date
  - Minutes, 1934-1939 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Minutes of Meetings, 1939-1942 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Bulletins, 1932-1941 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Bulletins - Rough drafts, notes, correspondence, 1934-1940 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Certification of Incorporation, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Chicago, Ill. - Affiliate, 1929-1934 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Clippings, 1910-1942 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Financial Records/Correspondence, 1935-1939 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Forum on household employment, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Membership files, 1934-1939 (Box 1, Folder 11-12)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - New Haven, Conn. Council, 1940-1942 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Programs (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Promotional literature (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Proposals for a Voluntary Agreement in Household Employment (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Questionnaires - Instructions (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Recommendations in regard to the reorganization of the (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Relationship with Bryn Mawr College, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Research Project, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Series II. General Correspondence
  - Correspondence, 1927 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    Between Mrs. Raliegh Hansl & Hildegarde Kneeland, (Home Economist, U.S. Bureau of Home Economics) re "Use of Time by Homemakers Study" - includes questionnaires, forms, etc
  - Correspondence, 1930-1932 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    Between Amey Watson & Encyclopedia of Social Sciences re article by Watson - includes draft of article on domestic service; to Emma Gunther (Columbia University) from Mary Anderson, (Dir., U.S. Women`s Bureau) re copy of a thesis (copy attached); by Ardis Carr re placement of domestic workers'; request to Gunther asking her to speak at various functions & routine
  - Correspondence, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    To E. Gunther re speaking engagements; between Benjamin R. Andrews (Prof., Columbia University) from Anna Burdick (Fed. Agent for Industrial Education) re routine; to Andrews from Dorothy Wells (Nat'l. Bd. YWCA) re the YWCA reporting on their work of training household employees to Andrews from (Pres. AFL) Wm. Green re the organizing of domestic employees; to Dorothy Wells from Mary LaDame, (Assoc. Dir. U.S. Emp. Service) re incorporating the emp. service of YWCA with state services; to Andrews from Amey Watson re tentative proposals for working agreements in Household Employment; between Mary Anderson & Grace Coyle (Nat'l. Bd. of YMCA) re Nat'l. Code for household employees; between Andrews & Gen. Hugh Johnson (WRA) re need for Industrial Code for household workers & routine
  - Correspondence, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    January-June 1934. To Frances Perkins from Mrs. F.M. Chase (a domestic servant) re the need for a code for the domestic worker; to Henry Wallace from a farm worker; to Gunther from Marie White (training section - TVA) re questionnaires from the Home Econ. Service of the Office of Education; to Gunther from Irene Colwell, (secty. - Community Emp. Service, Atlanta, GA) giving details of the set-up & program of the Community Emp. Ser. Training School in Atlanta (5 p. letter); to Andrews from Amelia Doddridge re training for household workers by the Cleveland YWCA, asking for suggestions in setting up courses; to Gunther from Salvation Army, Inc. (Pittsburgh) re Nat'l. Comm. Not having a representative from Pittsburgh; from Katherine Gardner (Nat'l. Council of Churches) to Gunther re ordinance requiring physical examinations; & routine
  - Correspondence, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    July-December 1934. Letter to Mrs. F.D. Roosevelt from Nat'l. Comm. On Household Employment (unsigned) re the Committee's appreciation for her interest & willingness to act as honorary chairman & outlining the progress & activities of the Committee (3 p.); memos to Dorothy Wells from Emma Gunther re Program Committee meeting - January 21-22; from Mary Dreier (Women's City Club of NY) to Gunther re problems of setting up standards for household workers; completed form re Nat'l. Committee for Public Administration Clearing House which gives purpose & activities of the organization; report on program committee meeting, November 1934; misc. undated & routine
  - Correspondence, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    January-March 1935. Letter to Gunther from YWCA (Providence, R.I.) re their activities concerning classes for domestic workers; Gunther from City of Grand Rapids, Michigan re regulation for household employment; Gunther from Maude King (Syracuse Univeristy) re university women as household employees - statistics from questionnaires; to Andrews from Pennsylvania State Employment Service re setting up a training course in Philadelphia for household employees; between John B. Andrews (American Association for Labor Legislation) & Benjamin Andrews re study for the need of accident compensation; to Gunther from Amey Watson re routine; to Andrews from Anna Burdick (U.S. Office of Education) re Washington School of Household Employment; & routine
  - Correspondence, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    April-May 1935. To Dorothy Wells from Benjamin Andrews re attached paper by Laura I. Baldt entitled "Liveries & Uniforms for Household Employees", 6 p. & the possiblility of publishing it as a bulletin of the Committee; between Lucy Mason (Nat'l. Consumers League) & Gunther re legislation in California including domestics in the hours law; routine correspondence between Watson & Gunther; many requests for bulletins & training courses; & other routine
  - Correspondence, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    June-December 1935. Many requests for the Committee's publication, "Volunteer Agreements between Employer & Employee"; & other routine
  - Correspondence, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    Requests for publications; from Gunther to NBC Studios re skit on household employment, entitled, "Let's Talk It Over", 6 p.; to Wells from Anna Burdick (U.S. office of Education) re statement for Social Work Yearbook, "Training for Household Employment", 2 p.; letter to Andrews from a household worker re wages, hours, etc.; to a household employee from Wells replying to her letter of complaint re hours, wages, etc. & routine
  - Correspondence, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    January-May 1937. Routine requests for publications; correspondence between Watson & Wells & between Watson & Gunther re conference & the possibility of getting a foundation to back a research project financially; correspondence between Wells & Eva Von Baur Hansl, including l0 p. mss. By Hansl, entitled, "Dignity for Domesticity"; correspondence & proposals for a voluntary agreement on household employees from Urban League of Pittsburgh
  - Correspondence, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    June-July 1937. Correspondence re research project - working out a proposal & obtaining funding, meetings, etc.; letter from Frances Perkins to Wells re support of research project; from Urban League of Pittsburgh to Wells re household workers training in Pittsburgh
  - Correspondence, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    August-September 1937. Copy of form letter sent out by Committee appealing for financial assistance & replies for same (same as file folder 32) & routine
  - Routine re publication requests, etc., 1937-1939 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    October-December
  - Routine correspondence of Dorothy P. Wells, Chairman, National Board, YWCA, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    January-April 1938
  - Correspondence, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    May-December 1938. Correspondence between Amey Watson & Dorothy Wells re leadership of the Nat'l. Comm. On Household Employment 5/24/38; and attendance at the Int'l. Management Conference 9/38; correspondence with Dorothy Wells re future of Nat'l. Committee, shortage of funds, possible merger with Women's City Club of New York City and routine
  - Correspondence, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    January-April 1939. Includes a report sent 3/2l/39 re conference on housekeeper service held under the auspices of the Children's Bureau, U.S.D.O.L., 11;6/37. l0 pp.; minutes of Sub-Committee on Selection of Chairman & New Members, Nat'l. Comm. On Household Employment, 3/25/39. 2 pp; correspondence re Dr. Erna Magnus' research project; 5 p. paper read by Amey Watson, "Next Steps in Household Employment", & routine
  - Correspondence, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 38)
    May 1939. Correspondence re relationship between Nat'l. Comm. And Bryn Mawr College; Dr. Erna Magnus' study 5/l8; includes a suggested plan for the relationship between Nat'l. Council & Bywr College 5/23; & routine
  - Routine Correspondence, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    June-August
  - Correspondence, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 40)
    September-December 1939. Includes "Notes on Meeting of the Interim Executive Committee, Nat'l. Council on Household Employment" ,9/26/39; correspondence re search for officers for the Nat'l. Council; minutes of meeting of Philadelphia members of the Nat'l. Council, 11/29/39; & routine
  - Correspondence, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 41)
    Correspondence with Wayne W. Light Co. re upcoming publication of "Her Book" and draft of "Servants Are People"; & routine
  - Correspondence, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 42)
    Includes report on the Minnesota Industrial Conference; memos of the Nat'l. Youth Admin. on Food Preparation; and other correspondence re household employment educational programs all addressed to Benjamin R. Andrews
  - Correspondence, 1942-1943 (Box 1, Folder 43)
    Responses to B.R. Andrews request for information re household employees including workmen's compensation laws in various states; Summary of Discussion on Household Employment in War-Time, Philadelphia, 4/30/42; & routine; also includes undated material
- Series III. Conference(s) - on employee-employer relationshiops in the home, 1928 and 1931 (and others)
  - Sub-Series A. Correspondence
    - Correspondence, 1928 (Box 2, Folder 1-5)
      January-October 11, 1928. Includes correspondence re articles for Women's Press; correspondence re arrangements, scheduling, invitations & replies, suggested general program & topics for a conference on Employer-Employee Relationship in the Home; report on Camp Gray domestic worker questionnaire and Camp Gray Industrial Conference, 5 pp.; replies to invitations to the conference include problems most frequently confronted in employer-employee relationships in the home
    - Correspondence, 1928 (Box 2, Folder 6-8)
      October 12-December, 1928. Correspondence re formation of a Nat'l. Committee on Employer-Employee Relationships in the Home including invitations to be on the new committee and attend the first meeting on December 8
    - Undated Correspondence (Box 2, Folder 9)
      Letter asking Mrs. F.D. Roosevelt to speak before the Parents' League of Greenwich (CT) & routine
    - Correspondence, 1929 (Box 2, Folder 10-11)
      Correspondence includes list of persons who agreed to become members of the National Committee; a Tentative Plan of Organization (4/29/29); arrangements for a luncheon meeting; correspondence re financial need for contributions; re activities & proposed work of the Committee; letter to Carner from Watson (Dec. 13, l939) re Mrs. Ford's refusal to see Watson while in Detroit.
    - Correspondence, 1930 (Box 2, Folder 12)
      January-May 1930. Between Watson and Lucy P. Carner (Executive, Industrial Dept., YWCA) re need for a course for study groups of employees; between Watson & Eva Von Baur Hansl re Nat'l. Comm. Functins; between Lawrence K. Frank (Rockefeller Foundation) & Watson re his comments on the program & report; & routine
    - Correspondence, 1930 (Box 2, Folder 13)
      July-October 1930. Resignation of Amey Watson as Vice-Chmn. Of Nat'l. Committee on Employer & Employee Relationships in the Home and the interest in the code of ethics for household employees; meeting arrangements & announcements; letter from Eleanor Roosevelt turning down offer to head the Committee; to Carner from Mary Anderson (U.S. Women's Bureau) re routine; other routine correspondence
    - Correspondence, 1930 (Box 2, Folder 14)
      November-December 1930. Correspondence between Garner, Anderson & Watson re the chairmanship of the committee & the possibility of changing the name of the committee; & other activities of the committee
    - Correspondence, 1931 (Box 2, Folder 15)
      January 1931. Correspondence between Watson, Carner & others re setting up additional planning meetings & problems of unemployment on household workers; & conference arrangements; letter from Frances Perkins, 1/2l/3l sending her regrets at not being able to attend a luncheon
    - Correspondence, 1931 (Box 2, Folder 16)
      February 1931. Re problems within committee - delay of conference decided; list of National Comm.; re continued search for permanent chairman
    - Correspondence, 1931 (Box 2, Folder 17)
      March 1931. Re plans for conference; form letters re the conference; acceptances & regrets
    - Correspondence, 1931 (Box 2, Folder 18)
      April 1-10, 1931. Re plans for conference; form letters re the conference; acceptances & regrets
    - Correspondence, 1931 (Box 2, Folder 19)
      April 11-27, 1931. Re plans for conference; form letters re the conference; acceptances & regrets
    - Correspondence, 1931 (Box 2, Folder 20)
      May-June 1931. Letter from Mrs. Roosevelt turning down offer of chairmanship (5/2/31) from Mary Anderson to Benjamin Andrews re Secretary of Labor possibly doing a survey of household employment; requests for findings of the recent conference; search for permanent chairman; letter including one from E. Roosevelt approving Mrs. Ethel Howes as a member & routine
    - Correspondence, 1931 (Box 2, Folder 21)
      July-September 1931. Correspondence re various articles written about household employees; re preparation of the summary of the conference; & routine
    - Correspondence, 1931 (Box 2, Folder 22)
      October-November 1931. Includes form letter sent to committee members from Lucy Carner re the continued search for a chairman & replies; Mrs. Roosevelt replies that Fanny Hurst may be a possibility for chairman; & other routine
    - Correspondence, 1932-1934 (Box 2, Folder 23)
      Correspondence between Watson, Carner & Andrews re publishing the material of the National Committee; & misc.
  - Sub-Series B. Conference Documents
    - Biography - re household employment (Box 2, Folder 24)
      8 pp, not dated
    - Bulletin - Household Employment Bulletin, 1933 (Box 2, Folder 25)
      National Committee on Employer-Employee Relationships in the Home, No. l, July 20th, l933
    - "The Conference of the National Committee on Employer-Employee Relationships in the Home - And What Led Up To It,", 1931 (Box 2, Folder 26)
      6 pp
    - "Conferences on Household Employment, Under the Auspices of - National Committee on Employer-Employee Relationships in the Home, 1928-3l,", 1928-1931 (Box 2, Folder 27)
      23 pp (draft copies)
    - Conference Minutes, 1928 (Box 2, Folder 28-29)
      Transcript of "Conference on Employee-Employer Relationships in the Home, October l7, l928. 2l3 pp
    - Executive Committee, 1934 (Box 2, Folder 30)
      5 page form letter from B. Andrews, Acting Chairman to Executive Committee re plans for the future
    - Financial, 1931 (Box 2, Folder 31)
      correspondence, reports, statements re National Committee expenses
    - History, 1928 (Box 2, Folder 32)
      3 pg brochure
    - Invitations, acceptances, etc. Includes lists, correspondence, etc., 1931 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Lists of those attending and not attending, 1928 (Box 2, Folder 34)